Guide to the Aaron Columbus Burr Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Aaron Columbus Burr papers
1838-1871
MS 116
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist of correspondence and business papers of Aaron Columbus Burr, merchant of New York City and adopted son of Aaron Burr. The papers relate to an attempt by Burr and James Grant to establish a colony for freed American slaves in Honduras. There is also material relating to the American Honduras Company, a firm formed by Burr and Grant for the cutting and exporting of mahogany.
Burr, Aaron Columbus, ca. 1808-1882
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection also available on microfilm (1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM54.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 54 instead of the originals.
Scope and Contents
The Aaron Columbus Burr (circa 1808-1882) Papers, 1838-1871, consist of correspondence and business relating to an attempt by Aaron Columbus Burr and James Grant to purchase a tract of land known as Stand Creek in British Honduras. After purchasing this land they planned to sell it to the United States in the hope that it would be used for colonizing freed American blacks. When this scheme failed, the American Honduras Company was formed to cut and export mahogany.
The correspondence is concerned mainly with the attempt to establish a colony in British Honduras. Notable correspondents include Hamilton Fish, James Grant, and Anna Ella Carroll. Among the business papers are the proposal for the founding of a colony for freed American slaves, descriptions of the lands in British Honduras, and documents relating to the mahogany industry.
Business; Slavery -- United States; Honduras; Latin America; Merchants; Burr, Aaron Columbus, ca. 1808-1882; Carroll, Anna Ella, 1815-1894; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893; Grant, James; American Honduras Company
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - 1840-1861 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - 1862-1866 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - 1867-1869 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - 1869-1871, undated (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Proposals to found a colony in British Honduras for freed slaves, and other related papers, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Legal and financial papers relating to the American Honduras Company, 1838-1870 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Descriptions of land in British Honduras, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - Reports, estimates, sale announcements relating to the mahogany industry, 1862, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Miscellaneous notes, newspaper clippings, order for tools, 1860, 1862, undated (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)